"The Safety and Efficacy of Ketogenic,
Low-Carb Diets for Diabetes Remission"
The effect of a plant-based,
low-fat diet
versus an animal-based,
ketogenic diet
on caloric intake
and weight loss.
A plant-based diet without
sugary refined grain foods
versus a keto diet
with a lot of vegetables.
After two weeks randomized
to one of the two diets,
the participants were switched
to the other one
for another two weeks.
Looking at the scale, guess
who lost more body weight?
Those on the low-carb diet.
But guess who lost
more body fat?
Those on the low-fat diet.
In fact, there was
no significant fat loss
on the low-carb diet,
whereas two pounds
(1 kg) of fat were lost
on the low-fat diet.
What they were losing
on the low-carb diet
was fat-free mass,
like water weight
but muscle, too.
While fat-free mass
was relatively preserved
while on the low-fat diet,
fat-free mass decreased
on the low-carb diet,
and there was evidence
that the participants
were losing muscle mass
despite eating more protein
than when they were
on the plant-based diet.
But when they were eating
almost no carbs,
their blood sugars
were certainly lower.
Does a ketogenic diet
have a place
within diabetes
clinical practice?
It's even been suggested
that low-carb diets
could put type 2 diabetes
into remission,
which can be defined
as an HbA1c,
a marker
of blood sugar control,
lower than 6.5 percent
for at least three months
after stopping any blood
sugar-lowering medications.
But high blood sugars
are just the symptom.
The disease is one
of carbohydrate intolerance.
If you're allergic to peanuts
and don't have symptoms
because you avoid peanuts,
you're just
managing the disease,
not curing it.
Curing a peanut allergy
would mean being able
to eat peanuts like anyone
without a peanut allergy.
It's the same with carbohydrates
and type 2 diabetes.
True remission
would be being able
to eat carbohydrates
like everyone else
without getting adverse effects.
As Dr. Greger has covered,
low-carb diets can actually
make diabetes worse,
worsening insulin resistance
and increasing intolerance
to carbohydrates.
That would only
be a problem, though,
if you resumed
eating carbohydrates.
Why not just stick
to a ketogenic diet forever?
What is the efficacy
and safety of low-carb diets
for type 2 diabetes remission?
First of all, it didn't work.
Using the,
"Under 6 .5 percent
and off all
diabetes medications"
definition of remission,
there was no significant
effect at six months
and at 12 months
there was less remission,
meaning more diabetes
in the low-carb groups,
along with clinically important
harms on quality of life
and, the deal-killer,
an increase in LDL cholesterol.
LDL cholesterol,
commonly known
as bad cholesterol,
is unequivocally recognized
as the principal driving force
in the development
of atherosclerotic
cardiovascular disease,
the leading cause of death
for both men and women.
Basically, we should try
to get our LDL
as low as possible.
Lower for longer is better.
Even if our LDL is normal,
even if other
heart disease risk factors
are considered optimal,
it is of utmost importance
to control our LDL.
If LDL is the primary driver
of our primary killer,
then if we could just know
one thing about a diet,
if there were only
one question we could ask
about some new diet
someone tells us about,
it would be,
"What does this diet do
to my LDL cholesterol?"
If you follow people
on lower carb diets over time
and see what happens
to their coronary artery
calcium scores,
which signify the progression
of coronary artery disease,
you'll find
that the low-carb group
had the highest incidence
of coronary artery
calcium worsening,
though this was only the case
with animal-based
low-carb diets,
not plant-based ones.
But those who started
eating low-carb diets
rich in animal protein and fat
in early adulthood,
had an increased risk
of coronary artery
calcium progression
in middle age.
Of course, all carbs
are not created equal.
Carbs that are
detrimental to our health,
like sugars and refined grains,
need to be distinguished
from those
with beneficial effects.
When the American
Heart Association
looked at dietary patterns
at a population level
and ranked them from
the most to the least aligned
with its dietary guidance
for heart health,
how did
low-carbohydrate diets rank?
Poorly.
In fact,
they were ranked the worst.
Even when very low-carb diets
are followed optimally,
they promote restriction
of foods considered
essential to heart health,
like legumes and whole grains,
and include
high-saturated-fat sources
like meat and dairy,
which are both
strongly discouraged.